Wilton Historical Society Map Collection
Wilton History Room, Wilton Historical Society
Wilton Historical Society Map Collection
1614-1992
Wilton Historical Society (Wilton, Conn.)
MAPS
44 linear feet; 14 map drawers, 14 tubes, 3 boxes
Wilton History Room, Wilton Historical Society
The Wilton Historical Society Map Collection contains maps and atlases of Wilton and Fairfield County, Connecticut, in addition to local blueprints, plans, charts, and lists of cartographical interest. The collection as a whole provides snapshots of Wilton since the 1700s, mapping Wilton businesses, homes, residents, and place names, showing developments in transportation, environment, and economy, and reflecting continuity and change in local cultures. The oldest dated items are photocopies, tracings, or drawings of originals; the earliest originals are from the mid- to late 1700s. The latest additions are from the end of the twentieth century.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the Wilton Historical Society Map Collection was compiled by the Wilton Historical Society, with select items donated by individuals and families.
History
1. Wilton Historical Society Map Collection
The Wilton Historical Society, founded in 1938, collected maps and related items of cartographical interest pertaining to Wilton, Fairfield County, and those portions of New York bordering Wilton. Additions have been made by Carol Russell, Wilton Historical Society Archivist and Wilton Town Historian. The majority of the material included in the collection was created by land surveyors and professional cartographers, with a few items independently produced by local Wiltonians. Local and state governments commissioned the bulk of items in the collection. Some materials were commissioned or amended by local chapters of national organizations, such as the League of Women Voters. A number of items in the collection have been annotated by Wilton historian G. Evans Hubbard.
2. Wilton History Room
The Wilton History Room is a unique collaboration between the Wilton Historical Society (WHS) and the Wilton Library Association (WLA). Compiled beginning in 1938, the archival collections of the Wilton Historical Society had been stored in the 18th century Fitch House. In 1980, the officers and trustees of the WHS, in conversation with the director and board members of the WLA, determined that a climate controlled space, improved organization, and better public accessibility were necessary; and so in January 1984 they established a home for the collection in the Wilton Library. Organization of the collections was supported by the Cudlipp Memorial Fund and undertaken by Carol Russell. The Wilton Historical Society has retained its ownership, while the Wilton Library maintains the collections, and provides access and assistance to patrons.
The Wilton History Room is one of the most complete, organized, and well-staffed historical research facilities, for a town of our size, in Fairfield County. It is supported by the WHS, the WLA, The Russell Fund, The History Room Fund, local non-profit organizations, individual donors, and community volunteers.
Today, the original archival collections of the WHS take up half of the Wilton History Room. Another quarter are library items. The collected papers of local organizations comprise the remainder: Cannon Grange, Children's Theater, Daughters of the American Revolution, Hurlbutt Street School House Association, Kiwanis Club, League of Women Voters, Rotary Club, Town Association, Weir Farm Stewardship Committee, Wilton Garden Club, Wilton Land Conservation Trust, Wilton Library, Wilton Playshop, Wilton Woman's Club, and more.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Wilton Historical Society Map Collection provides snapshots of Wilton and its environs beginning in the early 1700s. There is a special emphasis throughout on property boundaries and borders with adjacent communities, roads and infrastructure, the locations of homes and names of residents, government and elections, school districts, places of business and industry, and the minutiae of local names and landmarks both permanent (such as Split Rock) and ephemeral (including chestnut stumps and stone piles). Major historical events, in contrast, are less well represented. The collection nevertheless contains important examples, notably a map of General Tryon's Raid during the Revolutionary War and another showing important sites associated with African American history and the Underground Railroad's passage through the area.
Traced or photocopied land surveys in the collection map properties belonging to early Wilton families in the first half of the 1700s, including the Baldwin, Belden, Betts, Birchard, Buckingham, Comstock, Hickcox, Stuart, Keeler, Kellogg, Ketchum, Lambert, Marvin, Olmsted, Platt, Resseguies, St. John, and Whitney families.
Original maps and traced or photocopied land surveys of Wilton neighborhoods in the collection include Belden Hill, Cave Woods, Keeler's Ridge, Kent, Ketchum Bogs, Lambert Corners, Quarry Head, Split Rock, Wilton Center, and many others.
Adjacent communities represented in the collection include Georgetown (Redding), New Canaan, Norwalk, Ridgefield, and Salem, New York.
Arrangement
Arrangement of the collection is by the materials' physical properties, and by their availability for purchase. Individual non-salable items are stored as appropriate in tubes, map drawers, or on shelves. Map copies available for purchase are stored separately in two dedicated map drawers.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
American Revolutionary War, 1775-1783.; City planning.; Historic buildings.; Ridgefield, Battle of, Ridgefield, Conn., 1777.; Homes.; Real property--Connecticut--Fairfield County--Maps.; Road maps.; Transportation--Maps.; School districts.; Tryon, William, 1729-1788.; Neighborhoods.; Underground Railroad.; Zoning--Connecticut--Wilton (Town)--Maps.
Related Collections
Researchers interested in the history, locations, and boundaries of Wilton family properties and homes should also search for content organized by family names and historical locations of residence in the Wilton History Room's other collections, particularly Manuscripts and Neighborhoods. Property histories of select Wilton families and individuals are also narrated in Robert Russell's Wilton, Connecticut: Three Centuries of People, Places, and Progress. Finally, the Card File is helpful in locating specific family names mentioned in the early division of Wilton lands and the Norwalk Land Records.
Separated Material
Select additional maps are housed at the Wilton Historical Society Museum. Originals of pre-1802 land surveys, part of the Norwalk Land Records, are in the collections of the Norwalk Historical Society in the Norwalk History Room, Norwalk Public Library.
- 1. Aerial surveys, roads, and highways
  - Map of Wilton, Ridgefield, and New York, 1939; With names of residents. (Box 24, Folder MC 6-1)
  - League of Women Voters - Map of Wilton, 1950-1960; Maps for 1950, 1955, and 1960. (Box 24, Folder MC 6-2)
  - Right of way maps - Wilton Center - Connecticut State Highway Department, 1929-1935 (Box 24, Folder MC 6-3)
  - Wilton and vicinity: Roads, trails, and bridle paths, 1935-1953; Another copy is located in T5. (Box 24, Folder MC 6-4)
  - Town roads of Wilton - Connecticut State Highway Department, 1948-1951 (Box 24, Folder MC 6-5)
  - Wilton aerial map - Wilton Center, 1934 (Box 24, Folder MC 6-5)
  - Wilton aerial map - Belden Hill Road area, 1934 (Box 24, Folder MC 6-6)
  - Wilton road map, circa 1930; With names of residents. (Box 24, Folder MC 6-7)
- 2. Annotated, original, and rare maps of Wilton
  - Wilton parish, 1727 (Box 24, Folder MC 1-1)
  - Wilton, 1856; Cut out of Clark's map of Fairfield County, Conn. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-2)
  - Georgetown, 1856; Cut out of Clark's map of Fairfield County, Conn., showing residents. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-3)
  - Wilton roads, 1740-1986; Negatives and original. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-4)
  - Map of residents, 1856-1976; With notes of then owners of old homes. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-5)
  - Town of Wilton, Fairfield County, Conn., circa 1867; From F. W. Beers' Atlas of New York and vicinity. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-6)
  - Wood, C. N. - Map of the Town of Wilton, 1912 (Box 24, Folder MC 1-7)
  - Map of the Town of Wilton, Conn., 1929; Corrected for The Wilton Association (Box 24, Folder MC 1-8)
  - Residents of Wilton, 1937; See also T13. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-9)
  - Residents of Wilton, 1909-1950; Includes notes on history of road names and openings. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-9)
  - Residents of Wilton, 1937; With G. Evans Hubbard's notes on acreage and mortgages held by owners. Map shows residents as of 1761 to 1783. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-9)
  - Residents of Wilton, 1937; Showing permanent and seasonal homes. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-9)
  - Wilton, Conn. - Occupations of householders by place of work and residence, 1937; See also 1937 map from "Studies of Suburbanization" in pamphlet box. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-9)
  - Map of Wilton, 1939; With G. Evans Hubbard's notes on dates of openings and closings of roads, old road names, and some property owners. Map depicts Wilton between 1703 and 1772. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-10)
  - Map of Wilton, 1939; With G. Evans Hubbard's notes on dates and owners of some houses in Wilton. Map depicts Wilton between 1713 and 1790. (Box 24, Folder MC 1-10)
  - Town of Wilton, 1950; Map by League of Women Voters. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-1)
  - Town of Wilton, 1955; Map by League of Women Voters. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-2)
  - Town of Wilton., circa 1867; F. W. Beers' Atlas of New York and vicinity, annotated with district names and additional home owners. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-3)
  - Map of residents, 1856-1963; Annotated with then owners of old homes on Ridgefield Road. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-4)
  - Map of part of Connecticut (Wilton) surveyed by United States Navy Coast Guard, 1838-1840; See parts 50, 51, 107, and 131 for Wilton. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-5)
  - Residents of Wilton, 1937; Taken from "Studies of Suburbanization" in Connecticut. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-6)
  - Town of Wilton, 1960; Map with indexes by name and location; by League of Women Voters. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-7)
  - Town of Wilton (Republican Committee) with names of property owners, 1944 (Box 24, Folder MC 2-8)
  - Georgetown (Redding), 1958; With home and resident name locations. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-9)
  - Georgetown (Redding), 1964; With home and resident name locations. (Box 24, Folder MC 2-10)
- 3. Land survey maps
  - Drawing of "Great Plain", 1723-1728; From Norwalk Land Records. (Box 24, Folder MC 5-1)
  - Survey maps of properties in Wilton, 1717-1734; Photostats. Properties of Stephen and Eunice Baldwin, and John and Samuel Belden (1736); John Belden (1731); James Betts (1726); Samuel Betts (1724-1725); Stephen Betts (1734); Joseph Birchard (1727); Reverend M. Stephen Buckingham (undated); Samuel Comstock (1730); Captain Samuel Comstock (1730, 1732); Benjamin Hickcox (1720); David Keeler (1733-1734); Ebenezer Keeler (1726); John Keeler (1727); Ralph Keeler (1725); Lieutenant Samuel Keeler (1728,1729); Nathaniel Ketchum (1726-1727); David Lambert (1733-1734); John Marven (1734); Nathan Olmsted and Joseph Whitney (1725); Joseph Platt (1729); Captain Joseph Platt (1724-1725); Rebeckah Platt (1729); Alexander Resseguies (1717,1722-1723); Joseph St. John (1717); Ensign James Stuart (1721); John and Samuel Stuart (1734); and Matthew St. John (undated). (Box 24, Folder MC 5-2)
  - Survey maps of properties in Wilton, 1717-1769; Tracings. Properties of Belden Hill (1725-1743); Benjamin Hickox (1723); Betts and Marvin (1720-1769); Buckingham (1729-1736); Captain Joseph Platt, west of Belden Hill (1725); Cave Woods (1740); John Belden (1730); John Keeler, Belden Hill (1727); Joseph St. Johns, Split Rock Farm (1717); Kent area (1736-1741); Ketchum Bogs (1723); Lieutenant Samuel Keeler and Samuel Kellogg (1727); Matthew St. Johns (undated); Nathaniel Ketchum, John St. John, and David Keeler (1727); Ralph Keeler, Belden Hill (1725); and Stephen Betts (1734). (Box 24, Folder MC 5-3)
  - Map of Wilton, 1834-1840 (Box 24, Folder MC 5-4)
- 4. Maps, atlases, and plans on shelves and in tubes
  - Maps and atlases on shelves
    - Atlas of Fairfield County, Conn. Dolph & Stewart, New York, New York., 1942 (Box 20, Folder M3)
    - Atlas of Fairfield County, Conn. Dolph & Stewart, New York, New York., 1931 (Box 20, Folder M3)
    - Atlas of New York and vicinity. F. W. Beers, A. D. Ellis, and G. G. Soule, New York, New York., circa 1867 (Box 20, Folder M2)
    - Atlas of New York City and the metropolitan district. William H. Whiting & Company, New York City, New York., 1915 (Box 20, Folder M1)
    - English Pilot. The Fourth Book., 1759; Descriptions of the West-India Navigation, from Hudson's Bay to the River Amazons; showing maps, courses, distances, ebbing and flowing of the sea, tides, currents. Owned by Elkanah Andrews in 1775. (Box 20, Folder M2)
    - Official Maps of New England. National Survey Co., Chester, Vermont., 1922-1925 (Box 20, Folder M1)
    - Smith, Allen R. Connecticut: A Thematic Atlas. Central Connecticut State College., 1974 (Box 20, Folder M1)
    - Street, land, ownership and pictorial atlas of Fairfield County, Conn. Dolph & Stewart, New York, New York., 1942; Two copies. Second copy is stored in Box M2. (Box 20, Folder M1)
    - Soil survey of Fairfield County, Conn., 1981 (Box M3, Folder M3)
  - Maps and plans in tubes
    - Emery - Worldwide proposed expansion plan, 1984 (Box 23, Folder MT 2)
    - SAR (Sons of the American Revolution) - Charter members, undated (Box 23, Folder MT 3)
    - Historic sites in the settlement of African Americans in Conn., showing the Underground Railroad, undated (Box 23, Folder MT 4)
    - Roads, trails, and bridal paths in Wilton and vicinity, 1935-1953 (Box 23, Folder MT 5)
    - Renovation and restoration of Old Town Hall, 1978; Architectural drawings by John Gardner Coffin, Architect. (Box 23, Folder MT 6)
    - Old Town Hall, circa 1935; Blueprints by the WPA. (Box 23, Folder MT 6)
    - Keeler’s Ridge, Quarry Head, and Harrison Smith Preserve, circa 1990; Aerial map. (Box 23, Folder MT 7)
    - Quarry Head - Wilton, Conn., 1992; Staking plan. (Box 23, Folder MT 8)
    - Maps of Redding, including Georgetown, 1958-1964; By the Republican Town Committee. (Box 23, Folder MT 9)
    - Dana Station, undated; Restoration blueprints. (Box 23, Folder MT 10)
    - Lambert Corners, 1963; Survey map. (Box 23, Folder MT 10)
    - Wilton Railroad Station - Relocation, 1977; Architectural plans. (Box 23, Folder MT 10)
    - Lambert Corners, 1972; Site plan. (Box 23, Folder MT 10)
    - Hunt, Malcolm - Map index to pre-1802 land record research, undated; See also NEI 280 through NEI 370. (Box 23, Folder MT 11)
    - Wilton map with resident names, 1912; C. N. Wood's map. (Box 23, Folder MT 12)
    - Wilton map with resident names, 1929; The Wilton Association map. (Box 23, Folder MT 12)
    - Wilton map with 2,600 residences, 1958; With key. Residences located by League of Women Voters. (Box 23, Folder MT 12)
    - Residents of Wilton, Conn., 1937 (Box 23, Folder MT 13)
    - Map of the Town of Wilton, Conn. Enlarged and corrected by C. N. Wood., 1909 (Box 23, Folder MT 15)
    - Wilton, Conn. - Directory map, 1950 (Box 23, Folder MT 16)
- 5. Maps available for purchase
  - Master copies, 1740-1950 (Box 24, Folder MC 3-M)
  - Wilton roads, 1740; 50¢ (Box 24, Folder MC 3-1)
  - Route of General William Tryon's raid, 1777; 50¢ (Box 24, Folder MC 3-2)
  - Map of residents, 1856; From Clarks' Atlas. $3.50 (Box 24, Folder MC 3-3)
  - Town of Wilton, 1867; From F. W. Beers' Atlas. $5.00 (Box 24, Folder MC 3-4)
  - Town of Wilton with school districts, 1867; From F. W. Beers' Atlas. 50¢ (Box 24, Folder MC 3-5)
  - Map of Town of Wilton, Conn., 1909; 2 (Box 24, Folder MC 3-6)
  - Map of Town of Wilton, Conn., 1922; 2 (Box 24, Folder MC 4-1)
  - Map of Town of Wilton, Conn., 1935; Dolph & Stewart's Atlas (1935). $1.50 (Box 24, Folder MC 4-2)
  - Residents of Wilton, Conn., 1937; 2 (Box 24, Folder MC 4-3)
  - Map of Wilton, 1939; Prepared for G. Evans Hubbard. $1.00 (Box 24, Folder MC 4-4)
  - Map of Wilton, 1950; 2.5 (Box 24, Folder MC 4-5)
- 6. Miscellaneous
  - Ambler farm - Aerials and maps, undated (Box 25, Folder N 3)
  - Wilton - Planning and zoning maps, undated (Box 25, Folder N 4, N 5, N 6)
  - Wilton - Land use maps, 1974-1980 (Box 25, Folder N 4-1)
  - Open space and watershed maps, 1978-1983 (Box 25, Folder N 4-2)
  - Wilton - Transfer Station map, 1974 (Box 25, Folder N 5-1)
  - Zoning map, 1946 (Box 25, Folder N 5-2)
  - Wilton Planning Commission - Road map and trail map, 1954 (Box 25, Folder N 5-3)
  - Central education and recreation complex and school and recreation center plan, 1976-1947; Plan by Joseph F. Whitney, Site Planner. (Box 25, Folder N 5-4)
  - List of Republican electors, Wilton, 1927-1939 (Box 25, Folder N 7-1)
  - List of Republican electors, Wilton, 1940-1959 (Box 25, Folder N 7-2)
  - List of electors, Wilton, 1948-1959 (Box 25, Folder N 7-3)
  - Wilton maps, undated; Laminated maps. (Box 25, Folder N 12)
  - Map of Silvermine District of Canaan Parish and New Canaan, 1700-1946 (Box 25, Folder N 14-1)
  - Map showing from Salem, New York, to Norwalk, Conn., 1777; Hand drawn from recollection. (Box 25, Folder N 14-2)
  - Map of Fairfield County, undated; Photostat of 1792 original showing industries and public buildings. (Box 25, Folder N 14-3)
  - Fairfield County, before 1802; Negative. (Box 25, Folder N 14-4)
  - The principal parts of Norwalk, 1847 (Box 25, Folder N 14-5)
  - Map of Fairfield County, 1855; Map focuses on the Georgetown area of Wilton, Weston, and Redding. (Box 25, Folder N 14-6)
  - Western Connecticut, undated; Copy of an original 1885 map. (Box 25, Folder N 14-7)
  - Norwalk, Conn., 1888; Map from The Norwalk Hour. (Box 25, Folder N 14-8)
  - Map of central portion of the Norwalks, 1933 (Box 25, Folder N 14-9)
  - Silvermine is in Connecticut, 1945 (Box 25, Folder N 14-10)
  - Indexed street map of Norwalk, Darien, New Canaan, and part of Wilton (southwest corner), circa 1940; Map by Dolph & Stewart. (Box 25, Folder N 14-11)
  - Colony of Connecticut, 1774 (Box 25, Folder N 15-1)
  - Connecticut and parts adjacent, 1780 (Box 25, Folder N 15-2)
  - Connecticut from the best authorities, 1796; Photostat. From Benjamin Tanner's "The American Atlas, " an American edition of Winterbotham's Atlas. (Box 25, Folder N 15-3)
  - Map of Connecticut from actual survey, 1847 (Box 25, Folder N 15- 4)
  - Connecticut: Counties, boroughs, towns, 1850-1860 (Box 25, Folder N 15-5)
  - Section of map of Connecticut by Clark & Tackaburys, 1859; Positive and negative. Includes population figures. (Box 25, Folder N 15-6)
  - Tilden's new map of Connecticut, 1883 (Box 25, Folder N 15-7)
  - United States Geological Survey., 1889-1890; New York-Connecticut-Mt. Carmel Sheet and Connecticut-Danbury Sheet. The latter annotated in 1903 with homeowners. (Box 25, Folder N 15-8)
  - The heart of the Connecticut, 1912; Two books. Showing roads, towns, churches, schools, and population. (Box 25, Folder N 15-9)
  - Map of Connecticut Indian trails, villages, and sachemdoms, circa 1625; Copy. (Box 25, Folder N 15-10)
  - Coastal Connecticut including Wilton, 1838-1840; From the collection of Damon Douglas. (Box 25, Folder N 15-11)
  - Map of southwestern Fairfield County, Conn., and adjacent parts of Westchester County, New York, circa 1930; Map by Dolph & Stewart. (Box 25, Folder N 15-12)
  - The story of one corner of Connecticut in sixteen maps (reproductions of historical maps) covering the southeastern corner of the state, 1614-1935; (1) Captain John Smith’s map of New England in 1614; (2) Map of Connecticut, circa 1625; (3) Map of New England in 1677; (4) Connecticut and parts adjacent in 1777; (5) Old homes and homesites of Groton, Conn., circa 1935; (6) Benedict Arnold at New London in 1781; (7) Our corner of Connecticut in 1833; (8) Borough of Stonington in 1851; (9) Our corner of Connecticut in 1854; (10) The present-day Mystic area in 1854; (11) Groton Bank in 1868; (12, 13, 14) Noank, Poquonoc, and Old Mystic in 1868; (15) The Town of Stonington in 1868; and (16) Our corner of Connecticut in 1868. (Box 25, Folder N 15-18)
  - State of Connecticut - Highway system, 1938 (Box 25, Folder N 15-19)
  - The Connecticut Guide - May, 1935 (Box 25, Folder N 15-20)
  - A map of Connecticut and Rhode Island with Long Island, 1776 (Box 25, Folder N 15-13)
  - A new and accurate map of Connecticut and Rhode Island, circa 1780 (Box 25, Folder N 15-14)
  - Rhode Island and Connecticut, 1786 (Box 25, Folder N 15-15)
  - County map of Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Rhode Island, 1888 (Box 25, Folder N 15-16)
  - Map of the middle states of America, 1794 (Box 25, Folder N 15-17)